Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is דף נט עמוד
ב daf nun-tet amud bet and we pick up with the משנה
mishna on middle of נט עמוד ב. nun-tet amud bet. And if
the first three פרקים perakim of בבא מציעא Bava Metzia dealt with
objects, finding objects, being a שומר shomer on objects, then the fourth
and the fifth deal with money. So we've already dealt with the
whole issue about buying objects but ultimately the point was to determine
what constitutes כסף, kesef, right? What constitutes money? And especially money vis-a-vis
money, which one is the כסף, kesef, which one is the object.
And now we are moving on to, once we're dealing sort of
with that type of money focus, you know, we're moving on to
the whole issue about אונאה, ona'ah, about overcharging and how do you
figure out exactly how much somebody's being overcharged and what the consequences
of it are. And the next פרק perek will deal with the
issue of ריבית, ribbis, right? About charging interest. So the fourth and
the fifth פרק perek are really a focus on money
and they are some of the more challenging פרקים perakim in ש"ס.
Shas. So far, we've had it easy. I know somebody who complained
to me the other day and said, "Wow, it's been so hard."
I said, "What? That's been so hard? Just wait." So anyway, now,
I don't mean it's really been easy, but you know, the concepts
have been pretty straightforward, right? How do you do משיכה, meshicha, the
whole idea of מטבע matbe'a doing a משיכה, meshicha, you know, different
types of issues around that, about it being מי שפרע, Mi Shepara,
when you buy something and pay the money, is it already, you
know, is the transaction valid and you can reverse it or is
it still not, or you know, or does חז"ל Chazal have completely
overridden it? I mean, I think that there were nice little contained,
straightforward concepts, even you know obviously has the normal challenge of any
גמרא. Gemara. Anyway, now we get to the whole idea of overcharging
and it can be a little bit technical, but don't worry, I
will lead you through it. Okay? But just to give you a
sense of some of the challenge, if you take a look at
the תוספות Tosfos on today's דף, daf, the size of the תוספות
Tosfos on today's דף, daf, you know, no, no, no. When you
see a תוספות Tosfos that size, normally he's trying to reconcile like
five different גמרות, Gemaras, you know? This תוספות Tosfos is not trying
to reconcile any גמרא. Gemara. He's just trying to give פשט pshat
in our גמרא. Gemara. Like this is like a big רש"י, Rashi,
this תוספות. Tosfos. So when you see a תוספות Tosfos like that
that's just trying to give פשט, pshat, you know you got a
little bit of a trouble. But don't worry anyway, I'm going to
try to sort of simplify it all and hopefully we will successfully
make our way through this. So let's take a look at the
משנה. mishna. And we've this is the issue here of overcharging of
אונאה ona'ah and the פסוק pasuk in the תורה Torah says: וכי
תמכרו ממכר לעמיתך או קנה מיד עמיתך אל תונו איש את אחיו.
Vechi timkeru mimkar la'amitecha o kano miyad amitecha, al tonu ish et
achiv. What? אל תונו. Al tonu. Thank you.
אל תונו איש את אחיו. Al tonu ish et achiv.
So if you sell something to your friend and buy something from
your friend, do not oppress one man his brother. And it's clear
that in that context אונאה ona'ah means oppress, means don't overcharge, because
it says: במספר שנים אחר היובל תקנה מאת עמיתך במספר שני תבואות
ימכר לך, Bemispah shanim achar hayovel tikneh me'et amitecha, bemispar shnei tevu'ot
yimkor lach, something like that. Anyway,
that when you're buying property, you should understand that the יובל yovel
is coming and it's going to go back in the יובל yovel
and you're only buying the number of years until the יובל. yovel.
So make sure to charge appropriately. So clearly that issue of do
not oppress, don't do אונאה, ona'ah,
meant don't cheat in the act of the transaction of buying and
selling. Because it says when you sell and when you buy, interestingly,
there's an idea not only of אונאת לוקח, ona'at loke'ach, do not
overcharge the purchaser, but even אונאת מוכר, ona'at mocher, do not undercharge
the seller. You might think that the seller sets their business, it's
their responsibility to know what the going rate is and they're to
blame if they did not, you know, if they're the initiator usually.
If they're the one that's choosing to sell and they set too
low of a price, you know, you should say that that's a
problem, that that's their responsibility. But nevertheless, you know, and we might
see some lack of parallel between the buyer and the seller, but
nevertheless there's an equal prohibition to not underpay the seller.
Now, the irony is, two important definitional points and then we'll turn
to our משנה. mishna. Number one, although the פסוקים pesukim are, the
irony is that although the פסוקים pesukim are talking all about land,
right? That's the exact example they're giving. It's all there about in
the context about שמיטה Shmita and יובל yovel and the whole thing.
חז"ל Chazal tell us that there is no overcharging when it comes
to land, and that the whole פסוקים pesukim and the whole prohibition
only applies to cattle and מטלטלין. metaltelin. Whether the reason land is
excluded is because of a formalistic exclusion, like the same way, you
know, land isn't stolen and those types of issues that we've seen
before, or whether it is because, you know, of real estate, you
know, can have widely fluctuating property values, you know, more than a
camel, like, you know, cattle and so on,
that's a little bit up in the air because there is a
position of רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam that actually you can overcharge for
land if you charge more than twice the going rate. So, but
land interestingly is excluded, and the prohibition of overcharging relates to things
that are not land: movable property, cattle. The other interesting point to
note, or important point to note, and this is a point
I'm... five cents to make and you charge 500 dollars. And if
that's what people are willing to pay for this new widget that
you've made or whatever, געזונטערהייט, gezunterheit, okay? So the issue of overcharging
is charging more than the going rate. How exactly you determine the
going rate, I'm not exactly sure. You know you drive down the
highway and one place is selling gas for 2.19 and the other
place is gas for 2.49 three blocks later. I don't exactly know
how you'd determine the going rate, okay, whether you sort of do,
you know, but anyway that is the prohibition of over or under
charging. It's relative to the שער, sha'ar, the going rate. Yes.
Is אונאה ona'ah applied in a situation where someone develops something and
at first for a beginning period they can charge whatever they
want because other people haven't gotten into the... Right, that would be
true if other people could... now I don't know because what if
there is... no,
well first of all if you have like intellectual property and whatever,
but I mean חז"ל Chazal didn't know about intellectual property. But right,
but you know, but let's say everybody who gets into the business
decides they can all make a lot of money. Everybody can make
an exorbitant profit, right? So other people who are copying your invention
are also charging 500 dollars, you know. So it's not about the
amount of profit you make, it's about cheating somebody. And cheating is
defined by
charging a non-trivial amount more or less than the normal price of
this product would be. Yes.
Does אונאה ona'ah apply
to עבדים?
avadim? I do believe not. I believe it's excluded like קרקע. karka.
Yeah, I believe so. How do you explain then the
פסוקים pesukim in the Torah? It talks about עבדים. avadim.
What can I tell you, I mean I don't know, you know,
the פסוקים pesukim are... I don't know what to say to that.
Okay, it's a good point. I mean it's one of those cases
where it's so פשט. pshat. I mean all the illustrations in the
Torah are about land and we say no, technically that's not the
איסור issur of אונאה. ona'ah. I don't know what to say. Let's
take a look at the משנה. Mishnah.
Does that apply to price fixing and monopoly?
Oh,
that's an interesting question about price fixing. I mean they did deal
with like gouging people about essentials. You know there was a teaching
we had earlier that שמואל Shmuel said that you're not supposed to
you know charge more than a certain amount of profit for things
that are like basic essentials in life, you know, bread and milk
and wine and oil and whatever. But about price fixing I don't
know, that's a good point because yeah. Alright let's take a look
at the משנה. Mishnah. I mean the way I will say that
in history we've dealt with price fixing, you know there's a lot
of stories
about about like when the fish sellers charged a lot of money
for fish because everybody had to buy fish ערב שבת erev Shabbos
and the so like the rabbis of the time basically told people
it was אסור assur for them to buy fish until the price
went down and then the price went down. You know, so it
has but so it's been dealt with sort of by communal
response but it's not so clear that there's a direct הלכה halacha
about that. Alright let's take but that's a very good point. Let's
take a look at the משנה. Mishnah. האונאה ארבעה כסף מעשרים וארבעה
כסף
לסלע. Haona'ah arba'ah kesef me'esrim ve'arba'ah kesef lesela. So אונאה ona'ah is
charging you know
four מעות, ma'ot, you know, which are out of something that is
worth when they're out of 24,
they're basically... I mean
we don't really have to worry about this because really the bottom
line is it's four out of 24 which is one sixth, okay?
But anyway there are four מעות ma'ot to one... I gotta check
רש"י... Rashi... דינר. dinar.
And there are six דינר dinar to one סלע. sela. So there
are one סלע sela equals 24 מעות. ma'ot. Okay, so if something
is worth one סלע, sela, i.e. 24 מעות ma'ot and you are
overcharging by four מעות, ma'ot, okay, that is one sixth. So that's
a very complicated way of saying
שתות למקח. shtus lemekach. Thank you very much. One
sixth of the for the purchase... of the of the normal price
of the object. Okay, so basically if this is the standard price
of the object, don't overcharge by four מעות. ma'ot. Alright. עד מתי
מותר להחזיר. Ad matai mutar lehachzir.
Until when? So there's an immediate presumption that if you are overcharged,
what's the consequence of being overcharged? Right, the גמרא... Gemara... the משנה
Mishnah is not directly focusing on whether this guy has transgressed you
know the prohibition, it's about what the consequences are in terms of
business. So the immediate assumption is that if the guy has overcharged,
you have a right to reverse the sale. Okay, so until when
can you reverse the sale because you've been overcharged? עד כדי שיראה
לתגר או לקרובו. Ad kedei sheyera'eh letagar o lekrovo. The amount of
time that it takes to show a you know a like a
normal guy in business like somebody who's a buyer or a seller,
a merchant, thank you, or a relative. To get some other person's
informed advice about did I pay too much for this object. Now
תוספות Tosafot says that we're not going to assess each person and
say how far away does your relative live. where is the closest
merchant? We're going to establish a certain type of a normal fixed
time that it takes people normally to get advice. So whatever we
determine that time to be, three hours, whatever it is, that's the
amount of time for everybody. We're not going to do this as
a case-by-case assessment. Okay.
Now it would be 10 minutes with the cell phone.
I guess so. Well, you'd have to show them the object maybe,
but okay. But maybe. Right, exactly, yeah you can scan it. הלא
רבי טרפון בלוד, Hala Rabbi Tarfon belod, בלוד, belod, excuse me, האונאה
שמונה כסף מעשרים וארבעה כסף לסלע, שליש למקח. ha'ona'ah shemonah kesef me'esrim
ve'arba'ah kesef lesela shlish lamekach. He said actually it's not considered overcharging
until it's eight out of 24, a third. Okay, you could overcharge
a third and still be, up to a third it's still a
valid sale. Only after a third can this other side retract.
ושמחו תגרי לוד. vesamechu tigrei lod. So the merchants of לוד Lod
were rejoiced. Wow, we can get away with charging up to a
third over the going price, which by the way shows you that
even though yes there is an idea of a prohibition of underpaying,
classically the people who are going to be, you know, exploited and
taken advantage of are the buyers. The sellers are the ones that
are informed, it's their business and so on, so they're the ones
who classically have to be, you know, restricted. So here when you
say you can have a big amount before you define this אונאה,
ona'a, the people that are happy are not the buyers. Are not
the buyers. Right, it's the sellers that are happy. The sellers are
the ones that are classically overcharging. אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said
back to them, כל היום מותר לחזור, kol hayom mutar lachazor, but
you should know, I give people the whole day to reverse the
sale, not just a few hours.
אמרו לו, amru lo, they said to him, יניח לנו רבי טרפון
במקומנו, yanich lanu Rabbi Tarfon bimkomenu, רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon should leave
us the way we were before, וחזרו לדברי חכמים, vechazru ledivrei chachamim,
I think we'll go back to the חכמים, chachamim, sages' position.
You know, now of course since when do the merchants get a
choice to determine who are they פוסק'ן paskening like? But anyway, I
don't know the answer to that. But anyway, the point is is
that they would rather have a lower amount, a lower threshold of
how much they can get away with, but limit the time for
the person to retract because they basically just want the sale to
be final. So if you give a person like, you know, do
you give a person 30 days no return policy or a three-day
return policy? Right, so you'll get away with more if you have
a shorter amount of a return policy. So let's take a look
at the גמרא, Gemara, so what we have to figure out, the
גמרא's Gemara going to figure out exactly how do you compute the
sixth. But the other big thing to figure out is also what
is the consequence of overcharging, undercharging? All we know in the משנה
Mishna is there is a way in which you can reverse the
sale. But, you know, but there's going to be, just so you're
aware, there's going to be three basic stages or three basic things.
Okay, there's basically, here it's from zero, the going rate. The going
rate
to
a sixth, okay,
and then this is more than a sixth. Okay. So if you're
if it's under a sixth, what's the consequence? Can you get your
money back if you were undercharged? What's the consequence if you were
charged exactly a sixth? What's the consequence if you were charged more
than a sixth? Now from the משנה, Mishna, what,
or a sixth, right?
Yeah, we'll worry about רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon later. Okay, now from
the משנה, Mishna, you would think there's really only two. You would
think there's under a sixth maybe it's like that's a tolerable overcharge
and you know there's got to be a range anyway and like
nothing happens there and from, oh I'm sorry, I'm saying a third
I meant I'm sorry I'm sorry I meant to say a sixth,
you're right you're right. Thank you thank you. Okay, up to a
sixth. Okay, we'll get to we'll get to רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon
later, thank you. So from the משנה, Mishna, you would think there's
only two stages. Up to a sixth is a tolerable overcharge, from
a sixth and beyond that's overcharging and overcharging has from the משנה
Mishna sounds like one consequence, the side can basically, you know, retract
the sale. Okay, we are going to see that the גמרא Gemara
is going to deal with three stages: under a sixth, a sixth,
more than a sixth, okay, and there are two possible consequences. If
I'm the side that got overcharged, well three is nothing. Okay, but
if I'm the side that got overcharged, what do you think are
two possible ways I would like to get redress from this situation?
Reverse the sale,
I want to get my money back, I want to reverse the
sale, or I want to get back the amount you overcharged. So
we're going to have to figure out, the משנה Mishna only mentions
reversing the sale. We're going to have to figure out under what
circumstances can you get back the amount you've charged, and we're going
to divide it not like the פשט pshat in the משנה Mishna
of two stages, but three stages. Under a sixth, a sixth, more
than a sixth.
Okay. Let me more than a sixth or less than a sixth.
Something's more than. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. Okay, but before we get there we're going to have to
figure out how do you compute the sixth, which you might think
is easy but it's not. אתמר Itmar was said. רב אמר שתות
מקח שנינו, Rav amar shtus mekach shaninu, it's a sixth of the
normal going rate of the object. ושמואל אמר שתות מעות נמי שנינו.
Ushmuel amar shtus maos nami shaninu. No no no, a sixth also
includes cases of a sixth of the amount you paid. Okay now
let's not guess, let's just read it. Okay, now שוי שיתא בחמשה.
shavi shisa bechamsha. שוי שיתא בשבעה, shavi shisa b'shiva, כולי עלמא לא
פליגי דבתר מקח אזלינן kuli alma lo peligi d'vasar mekakh azlinan ואונאה
הוי. ve'onaya hvei. Okay? So if the object should be six, that's
the going rate, and instead you charged five, so it was underpaid,
or seven, okay, so that is a sixth of this. You start
by the going rate, okay, that's the going rate, that's what the
object is worth we're going to say. A sixth of the object
is worth is one-sixth equals like a sixth is one, okay, so
a sixth of the going rate is one, so if you overcharge
by one or undercharge by one, you're in the אונאה ona'ah category,
you're in the overcharging category. So everybody agrees that one way to
determine the range is based on you start by the going rate
of the object, okay, and you go one, one in each direction.
That everybody agrees. Okay. כי פליגי, ki peligi, what's the debate, what
does שמואל Shmuel when שמואל Shmuel says you also look at the
money, what is שמואל Shmuel talking about? שוי חמשה בשיתא shavi chamsha
b'shisa and שוי שבעה בשיתא. shavi shiva b'shisa. So you have something
that is worth five,
wait hold on, שוי חמשה בשיתא shavi chamsha b'shisa that you, that
the guy paid, okay, was worth five but the guy paid six,
okay, now if we were to base it based on the issue
about the cost of the object, a sixth of five is what?
Five-sixths. Okay, so this would be more than a שתות. shtus. Now
as far as the משנה's mishna concerned, we only know of two
stages, under שתות shtus and a שתות shtus or more, but the
גמרא gemara actually knows of three stages, okay, so and the basic
point is going to be the following: this is going to be
considered exactly a sixth is going to be considered אונאה, ona'ah,
overcharging, but you basically can either reverse or get your money back,
and more than a sixth is called ביטול מקח, bitul mekakh,
okay, that's so grossly overcharged that the whole sale is בטל, battel,
okay, now תוספות tosafos I should say point out the irony of
this, because if this is that you have a choice and this
is that the whole thing is בטל, battel, if I'm the seller,
which situation would I rather? That the buyer who I have cheated
has a choice of getting his money back or annulling it, or
would I rather that it just gets annulled? Choice. You'd rather he
has a choice? Why would I want to give the buyer more
choices?
Maybe he wouldn't even notice.
No, well, he might, oh, so okay, so anyway, so you could
say, okay, so,
if it might depend if he notices, if regardless of him noticing
it automatically gets annulled, right, or automatically, you know, anyway, so the,
so let me just say it this way: there's a way of
arguing that I would actually rather it get annulled, because here why
would I want to give him more choices? Maybe I don't want
to give him the money back, like if I'm not going to
be able to, you know, if I have to give him all
the money back, you know, then I'd rather not have sold it
to him, so you might have argued that I would have rather,
you know, him have it just be annulled rather than give him
the choice of annulling, but תוספות tosafos says two answers to that,
one is what you said, one answer is I don't care what
you would rather, if you so grossly overcharged then we can't even
consider it a legitimate transaction, so even though it ironically could benefit
the seller because it limits the options of the buyer, but doesn't
matter, once it's a gross overcharge the whole thing is not a
legitimate transaction. The other way of תוספות tosafos saying it which might
make more sense which is what David said, he says, here
the basically
the buyer has to, wait now I'm trying to remember what תוספות
tosafos says, hold on a
second... yes, what he says is is that here,
alright I'm losing a little bit of the track, anyway תוספות tosafos
says the question is is that whether this is a ביטול מקח,
bitul mekakh, I have to think this through a little bit more,
but the question is is this a ביטול מקח bitul mekakh automatically
or is this only a ביטול מקח bitul mekakh if the guy
comes and complains, okay, so it could be that even this is
only a ביטול מקח bitul mekakh if the guy comes and complains
and demands and demands it back.
He can get away with it if he doesn't?
Yeah, I don't know, you know what, I shouldn't have gone into
that detail because now I'm losing a little track myself, let's bracket
some of that conversation for a moment.
Yeah, like a גלוי מלתא?
gilluy milta? Yeah, yeah, you know what, I'm going to bracket some
of that for now, I shouldn't have gone into that level of
detail, okay, right now the important thing is is that is that
at this stage it's אונאה ona'ah and the presumption is you can
choose whether get your money back
or get a, you know, get the
over... get the overcharge back
or ביטול מקח bitul mekach and here it is so grossly overcharged
that that's just it. It's ביטול מקח bitul mekach end of story.
Okay? So, there are three stages. So, if you're going from five
to six,
if we would only go by a sixth of the money, okay,
so when you hit five and five sixths, you would be אונאה.
ona'ah. And then this amount to go to, to go to from
five and five sixths to six, when you get to six, you
would be, yeah, this would be אונאה, ona'ah, this would be and
then from here here to here would be ביטול מקח. bitul mekach.
I mean, from here ad infinitum would be ביטול מקח, bitul mekach,
okay? So, that's how you would normally do it if you only
went by a a sixth of that. You hit five and five
sixths אונאה, ona'ah, anything more ביטול מקח. bitul mekach. Okay, people with
me? Comes along שמואל Shmuel and שמואל Shmuel says no, even between
five and five sixths and six, all of this is אונאה, ona'ah,
because this is still within one sixth of the amount you paid.
Okay? So so so if it's either a sixth of the of
the of here, so in this example, right, we start by saying
this is אונאה, ona'ah, I'm sorry, when you hit seven, you're at
אונאה ona'ah and here you're at אונאה ona'ah and then when you
go further, you're at ביטול מקח, bitul mekach,
okay?
Okay, right? That's normally. You hit the more than a more than
a sixth up a sixth you're at אונאה, ona'ah, more you're at
ביטול מקח. bitul mekach. All right, but so here you would say
if you started with five, you're at אונאה ona'ah more you're ביטול
מקח bitul mekach and שמואל Shmuel says no, we actually have a
range of אונאה, ona'ah, which makes sense, like why should there be
one precise point that's אונאה, ona'ah, right? He actually gives you a
little bit of a range. So whether it is a, so anywhere
from, right, it's you know about anywhere from a a sixth of
the price of the object to a sixth of the money that
you paid, that whole range is considered אונאה, ona'ah, and ביטול מקח
bitul mekach only starts after, okay? So שמואל Shmuel says you figure
out the sixth in two directions. A sixth of here, so אונאה
ona'ah starts here, and a sixth of you paid, so אונאה ona'ah
ends here and that ranges. One minute. Let's just do the other
example. Okay, אינמי inami says the גמרא, Gemara, or שוי שבעה בשישא.
shavi shiva beshisha. Okay, or let's say you're being undercharged. So seven
and it was charged six. Now, if I only look at the
price of the מקח, mekach, okay, what's a sixth of seven?
What's a sixth of seven?
One and one sixth. Okay, so so five and five sixths here,
right? Is that right? A sixth of seven is wait, no, seven
divided by six is one and yeah, one and a sixth. Okay,
that's right. So five and five sixths. So if I went by
if I went by אונאה ona'ah to if I went by the
going price, okay, I'm trying to make a square, that's the starting
price. If I went by the price of the object, this would
be אונאה, ona'ah. okay, that would be ביטול מקח bitul mekach
and this, this range all of this would be would basically be
just what's called מחילה. mechila. That would just basically be no consequence,
anything less than a sixth. Okay, so if you go by the
price of the object, again, this is what you have. שמואל Shmuel
says we also go by the amount paid. So if the person
paid six, well that is one, that's within right one that's one
sixth of a difference here between the amount paid and the amount
it was worth. So so אונאה ona'ah, starts here. So again for
שמואל, Shmuel, you've got a range of אונאה. ona'ah The range of
אונאה, ona'ah, it's not just one point, the sixth. The range of
אונאה ona'ah. is the space between a sixth of the a sixth
of the amount paid, okay, is where it starts, and it ends
with a sixth of the amount it was worth. Here, right, it's
a starts with a sixth of the amount paid and ends with
a I'm sorry, a sixth of what it was worth and ends
with a sixth of the amount that was paid.
Let me repeat that last part.
That's for שמואל. Shmuel. For for okay, for רב, Rav, there's one
point of אונאה, ona'ah. which is the one amount dollar amount that
is a sixth of the amount it was worth. This is the
one point of אונאה. ona'ah Before this is מחילה, mechila, after this
is ביטול מקח. bitul mekach. Okay, this is the one point of
אונאה. ona'ah, After this is ביטול מקח. bitul mekach. For שמואל Shmuel
אונאה ona'ah. is a range. It's a range of the space between
a sixth of the amount it was worth and a sixth of
the amount that was paid. That's the range. Okay, so here a
sixth of the amount that it was worth is five and five
sixths, a sixth of the amount that it was paid was six,
that's the range, okay? So שמואל's Shmuel got that range defined. by
the sixth of the value of the object and the sixth of
the amount paid. If you want to take a look at, I
figured this out, you'll be very impressed. Okay, what? You'll be very
impressed. I will figure this out. If the object, we'll put it
all on one graph. If the object is worth six, okay,
then a sixth of the amount of the object is, one-sixth of
the value of the object is one, right? So,
okay, going rate, right? So that would give you here at seven
and at five. That's our משנה. mishna. Okay, if you say, wait
wait wait, what would be a sixth of the amount that was
paid? Okay, so actually in this case, one minute, I had this
figured out.
Yes, it would be, I believe it is five and one-seventh here
and seven and one-sixth here. You can do the math. Okay, but
if you take a sixth of five and one-seventh, you'll get six-sevenths,
and that'll be a sixth of the amount paid. And if you
take a sixth of seven and one-sixth, you'll
get one and a sixth, so whatever, no maybe it's like whatever,
I don't remember, you'll figure it out. Okay, something like this. Anyway,
I had it all figured out. Anyway, okay, so this is, so
according to שמואל, Shmuel, it's, this is the אונאה, ona'ah. not just
this is the
אונאה. ona'ah. I've totally confused everybody? Okay, people pretty much got it?
Yes.
So I have another question. So if this is a ביטול מקח,
bitul mekach, if something happens in between, is it still my responsibility?
I bought it from you like you totally overcharged me. Like, am
I considered a שומר shomer on it?
All right, right, we'll worry about that later. Okay, all right, but
the basic point is that according to רב, Rav, it's a sixth
of the value and there's one point of אונאה. ona'ah And according
to שמואל, Shmuel, you also look at the amount paid. And since
once it's five and one-seventh, you are within a sixth, because a
sixth of five and one-seventh is, I think I got that right,
a sixth of five and one-seventh is six-sevenths, so that is within
a sixth. So a sixth here, that's where it begins, a sixth
of the amount you paid. So then this is a range of
אונאה. ona'ah. And here, right, a sixth of seven and one-sixth is
whatever, is one and a sixth or something like that, and therefore
this is a sixth,
seven and a sixth, right, so a sixth of that is one
and a sixth, so your range of אונאה ona'ah, ends at that
stage. So you've got a range of אונאה.
ona'ah, Meaning, you take five for something worth six and you take
a sixth of five.
Yeah, no, you take a sixth of six. This is the amount
paid, yes.
Yes, the amount paid, you take a sixth of five.
So for שמואל, Shmuel, there is a range of what's defined as
a sixth, between a sixth of the amount paid and a sixth
of what the object was worth.
All right, it's not obvious from the text.
No kidding, let's keep on reading. Okay, I think we got everybody
sufficiently confused. I had it so clear before.
I follow what you did, but I don't see that it's obvious
from.
Well, because I just put it on one chart. The גמרא Gemara
started dealing with different priced objects. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
No absolute value?
No absolute value, market rate. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Okay, ושמואל דאמר בתר דמי אזלינן, u'Shmuel d'amar batar d'mi azlinan, we
also look at the money. If you charged for something five, six,
or something six,
seven, אידי ואידי אונאה הוי, idi v'idi ona'ah havei, that's still within
the range of אונאה, ona'ah. because it is a sixth of the
price of, it is a sixth of the amount paid. לרב דאמר
בתר מקח אזלינן, l'Rav d'amar batar mekach azlinan, Rav says you only
look at the value of the object, so שוי חמשה בשישה, shavei
chamsha b'shisha, if you sold something worth five for six, so that's
more than a sixth of the value of the object, ביטול מקח
הוי, bitul mekach havei, you're in the third category of ביטול מקח.
bitul mekach. שוי שבעה בשישה, shavei shiva b'shisha, if you sold something
seven worth six, so if you only focus on the value of
the object, that's less than a sixth, מחילה הוי, mechila havei, so
you're in the lower category, right? So Rav has this one point
of אונאה, ona'ah, anything higher is ביטול מקח, bitul mekach, anything lower
is מחילה. mechila. שמואל Shmuel at least has a little bit of
a range of
אונאה.
ona'ah. Meaning, the seller is giving it away?
No, no, no. מחילה mechila means that the buyer is, has
doesn't have a right to ask for his money back. His overpayment
is within a tolerable range and he's not מקפיד machpid on the
amount that was overpaid. Okay?
He's מוחל mochel the,
he's מוחל mochel the overpayment? Well, in one scenario. Okay, whoever is
not paying the going rate is being מוחל mochel the difference. ושמואל
אמר, u'Shmuel amar, and Shmuel said, כי אמרינן מחילה וביטול מקח, ki
amrinan mechila u'vitul mekach, when do we say that you have when
it's lower than a sixth it's מחילה, mechila, more than a sixth
it's ביטול מקח, bitul mekach, היכא דליכא שתות משני צדדין, heicha d'leika
shtus mi'shnei tzidadin, only when it is neither a sixth in either
direction. אבל היכא דאיכא שתות מצד אחד, aval heicha d'ika shtus mi'tzad
echad, but if in any one way of computing it there's a
sixth, so in that case אונאה הוי, ona'ah havei, it's אונאה, ona'ah.
which basically means there's a range, okay, when you hit five, you're
at sixth from the going rate, when you hit five and a
seventh, you are at a sixth of the amount paid, and therefore
in that space is אונאה. Onaah So for it to be מחילה
mechilah or ביטול מקח bitul mekach it has to be outside of
that range. All right, so that's what שמואל Shmuel says. Yeah.
I just want to ask, I want to be clear on the
terms. I had thought that ביטול bitul was the situation in which
the seller overpaid and מחילה mechilah is when he underpaid.
Is that not true? No, it all just depends whether you're on
the seller side or the buyer side. Okay, meaning I will get
that. I will explain it then. Okay, here is the classic example
of overcharging. Less than a sixth, we assume that the amount that
the buyer overpaid, he's מוחל, mochel, like you know he tolerates overpaying
a certain amount. Okay, and he can't ask for it back. At
the exact one sixth or the range of a sixth, it's אונאה.
Onaah. He can either get his money back or he can retract
the sale. More than a sixth, the whole sale is בטל. batel.
It was way too way too grossly overcharged. The same would be
true if it is the seller being cheated. If he's underpaid up
to a sixth, then he tolerates being underpaid a little bit, he
right. If he's underpaid a sixth or the range of a sixth,
then he has the right to either get the extra money that
he was coming to him or to reverse the sale. If he's
underpaid more than a sixth, then the whole thing was a gross
you know gross undercharge gross underpayment and therefore the whole thing is
בטל. batel. So it's exact same thing, it's just depends which side
is being cheated, is being over or undercharged. Okay, let's take a
look now as the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, תנן, tnan, we learned
in the משנה. Mishnah. האונאה ארבעה כסף מעשרים וארבעה כסף לסלע שתות
למקח, Ha'ona'ah arba'ah kesef me'esrim ve'arba'ah kesef lesela shtut lamekach, one sixth.
מאי לאו דזבין שוין עשרין בעשרין וארבע. Mai lav dezavin shavin esrin
be'esrin ve'arba. You paid
now the גמרא Gemara assumes that what this means is that you
charged for something that was worth twenty, you charged twenty four.
Now think for a minute. If something worth twenty you charge twenty
four, what is a sixth of twenty? A sixth of twenty is
we're testing everybody's math skills. It's like three and some change. Right?
Okay. So if you charged for twenty twenty four, you've charged more
than a sixth of the value of the object, but it is
a sixth of the price. A sixth of twenty four is four,
so it's a sixth focusing on the price but not focusing on
the value of the object. So if that's true, that supports שמואל.
Shmuel. ושמע מינה שתות דמים נמי שנינו. u'shma mina shtut damim nami
shaninu. So you see that a שתות shtut would also be defined
by the amount paid. So the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, no.
דזבין שוין עשרין וארבע בעשרין. Dezavin shavin esrin ve'arba be'esrin. No no
no, the object was worth twenty four. That would I thought was
פשט pshat of the משנה Mishnah anyway. So a sixth of twenty
four is four and therefore the case is we're just going to
make it a case of undercharge. The guy only paid twenty for
an object worth twenty four, but we're figuring it based on the
value of the object. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. In
that scenario something worth twenty four was charged twenty, מי ניתני מוחל?
mi nitni mochel?
So who's being cheated? The seller. אימא סיפא, eima seifa, look at
the end. עד מתי מותר להחזיר בכדי שיראה לתגר או לקרובו. Ad
matai mutar lehachzir bichdei she'yira'eh letagar o likrovo.
You can retract until you can show to a merchant or your
friend. So now who's the person showing to a merchant or his
friend? The guy who bought it, not the guy who sold it.
So אמר רב נחמן, amar Rav Nachman, לא שנו אלא לוקח. lo
shanu ela lokeach. That's only the buyer, because he's got the object
and can show, אבל מוכר לעולם חוזר, aval mocher le'olam chozer, which
is bizarre. You because you could say the seller he doesn't have
the object to show, so maybe he needs more time to figure
out if he got the right price. But the irony is of
course the the seller is the one who should be more responsible
and that we should expect more has less of a claim that
he was cheated. Okay, but be that as it may, the point
still is is that clearly when the משנה Mishnah talks about showing
to your friend or a merchant, it's talking about the buyer. And
if a case that the buyer was cheated, was overcharged. So אלא,
ella, so it can't be twenty four was charged for twenty. The
case of the משנה Mishnah is that the buyer was cheated. אלא
דזבין שוין עשרין וארבע בעשרין ותמניא. Ella dezavin shavin esrin ve'arba be'esrin
vetamanya. Fine,
something
twenty four was charged twenty eight. So that's probably what I would
assume פשט pshat of the משנה Mishnah was. It's a sixth of
the value of the object. The object's worth twenty four, it was
overcharged, it was charged twenty eight. All right, so you can't prove
from that case of the משנה Mishnah which way רבא Rava or
שמואל. Shmuel. תנן, tnan, now. הורה רבי טרפון בלוד, Hora Rabbi Tarfon
be'Lod, האונאה שמונה כסף מעשרים וארבעה כסף לסלע haona shimona kesef me'esrim
ve'arba'a kesef lesela, שליש למקח. shelish lamikach.
So it's a third, eight out of twenty four. So the גמרא
Gemara is going to go through the same thing about this, you
know, it's like a straightforward answer but it's going to go through
it also. מאי לאו דזבין שוין שיתסר בעשרין וארבע. Mai lav dezavin
shavin shitesar be'esrin ve'arba.
It seems you're selling sixteen for twenty four. So that means that
you're figuring it out not by a third of the value of
the object, because then that would be only five. You're figuring it
out about a third about the amount paid. If you pay twenty
four, a third of that is eight. ושמע מינה שליש דמים נמי
שנינו. u'shma mina shlish damim nami shaninu.
You see you go by a third. amount paid because that's how
we constructed the case. So the Gemara says לא, Lo, no, דזבין
שוה עשרים וארבעה בשיתסר. Dezabin Shaveh Esrim Ve'arbaa Beshitasar. No, it's the
opposite. You pay something was worth 24, a third of that was
eight, and you paid only 16. So it is a third of
the value of the object. But again, the Gemara went
down. So the Gemara made it a that the seller was cheated.
One minute. מי נתאנה? Mi Nitana? מוכר? Mochar? According to that, 24
was sold for 16. The seller was cheated. אימא סיפא. Eima Seifa.
אמר להם כל היום עומד לחזור. Amar Lahem Kol Hayom Omed Lachazor.
You can go back the whole day. Okay. And the idea that
you know and ודאמר רב נחמן לא שנו אלא לוקח אבל מוכר
לעולם חוזר. Vede'amar Rav Nachman Lo Shanu Ela Lokeach Aval Mochar Le'olam
Chozer. The idea whether you have a few hours to go back
the whole day to go back is an issue about the buyer,
not the seller. So clearly the scenario is that it was the
buyer who was overcharged. Fine. So we'll make it that case. It's
going to be a third of the value of the object and
it's going to be that the buyer was overcharged. אלא דזבין שוה
עשרים וארבעה בתלתין ותרין. Ela Dezabin Shaveh Esrim Ve'arbaa Betlatin Vetarin. It
was worth 24, you charged 32. So it was a third of
the value of the object according to Rabbi Tarfon and it was
the buyer that was overcharged. All right. Bottom line is they just
construct the case of the Mishnah to fit. Okay. But the simple
anyway the simple read of the Mishnah is it's a third of
the value of the object like Rav and that amount the object
was worth 24, the
guy was overcharged either if it's a sixth of it they were
overcharged four and if it's a third of it they were overcharged
eight. Okay. But it's the value of the object. There's nothing in
the Mishnah that indicates it's the value of the money
that we have a range. Okay. So now the Gemara says like
this.
שמע. Shema.
Okay. תני כוותיה דשמואל. Tani Kevatei DeShmuel. We taught like Shmuel. מי
שהוטל עליו ידו על העליונה. Mi Shehotal Alav Yado Al Haelyona. The
person who was cheated, okay, is the guy who has the option
to choose how to get redress. כיצד? Keitzad? מכר לו שוה ה'
בו'. Machar Lo Shaveh Hei BeVav. Okay.
Something worth five was sold for six. מי נתאנה? Mi Nitana? Who
was cheated? לוקח. Lokeach. The buyer. It was overcharged. יד לוקח על
העליונה. Yad Lokeach Al Haelyona. So the לוקח Lokeach has the right
to choose what type of redress he wants. רצה אומר תן לי
מעותי. Ratza Omer Ten Li Maotai. He can either say give me
my money back. או תן לי מה שאוניתני. O Ten Li Ma
Sheonitani. Or he can say you know I'm sorry. תן לי מעותי
Ten Li Maotai excuse me means I want to reverse the sale.
Give me all my money back. או תן לי מה שאוניתני. O
Ten Li Ma Sheonitani. Or the sale we'll keep the sale but
give me the overcharge. All right. מכר לו שוה ששה בחמישה. Machar
Lo Shaveh Shisha Bachamisha.
However if something worth six was sold for five. So it was
undercharged. מי נתאנה? Mi Nitana?
Who was cheated? מוכר. Mochar. The seller. So if the seller was
cheated יד מוכר על העליונה. Yad Mochar Al Haelyona. The מוכר Mochar
has the options. רצה אמר לו תן לי מקחי. Ratza Amar Lo
Ten Li Mikchi. He can either say we're reversing the sale give
me my object back. או תן לי מה שאוניתני. O Ten Li
Ma Sheonitani. Or he can say pay me the amount you undercharged
you underpaid you
know pay me what you should have paid to have made it
a fair deal. Now the relevant point for us the relevant point
of this Baraita is to say that the person cheated has an
option and the options are either retract the sale or right אונאה
ona'ah, you can choose.
Either one
get the
extra amount that it was over or undercharged back or two ביטול
מקח. Bitul Mekach. So the point of this Baraita is that the
person cheated has a choice. But what were the scenarios we give
had a scenario of a sixth based on the money and a
sixth based on the value of the object. The first case was
something for five was sold for six. Okay. So that was actually
a sixth of the money paid. Because according to Rav a sixth
of the object would have been five and five sixths and anything
more than that would have been ביטול מקח. Bitul Mekach. So the
fact that we say something five sold for six is considered to
be a sixth of the object means we go by a sixth
of the amount paid. Is that clear? The second scenario was something
six was sold for five. That's your classic case of a sixth
of the value of the object. But this Baraita supports Shmuel because
it gives a scenario of a sixth figuring it either from the
value of the object or from the amount paid which means that
there is a range in which this period of אונאה. ona'ah Yes.
You're saying your read is the פשט Pshat of the Mishnah there's
no indication that it's talking about a sixth of the money paid
it's only talking about a sixth of...
Well it says...
because your only language used in the Mishnah is כסף. Kesef.
No it also says שתות למקח. Shtut Lemekach.
But it also says
all right so maybe that's why the Gemara thought that and I
won't debate it I don't know I won't debate it the Mishnah
is ambiguous. Let's go on in the Gemara. Okay. So the Gemara
says like this. איבעיא להו. Ibaia Lehu. So good. So now we
have the debate of Rav and Shmuel about whether there's a range
of a sixth or whether there's a pinpoint of a sixth. Shmuel
is more attractive not just because whether it's a better Baraita or
the read of the Mishnah it's more attractive because it's absurd to
have three categories where one category is one precise amount right
exactly a sixth has this consequence. Anything over under is either automatically
מחילה mechilah or automatically ביטול מקח. bittul mekach. So what is the
logic of having something such a precise amount? So if the idea
that there's a range at least makes a little more sense if
you're going to divide it up into three sections. Okay, but that
is anyway the debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. Okay, now
what we're going to look at is,
okay, we have these three things, okay, here is
what'd I do with my pen?
Okay, so it's going to be אונאה, ona'ah מחילה, mechilah, ביטול
מקח.
bittul
mekach. And now the question that's going to absorb us for the
rest of the דף, daf, we'll see how much we get through,
is when you have a right to retract, okay, which of these
three stages do you have that right to retract for a limited
period of time? Clearly we're going to assume because we are assuming
the משנה Mishnah is talking about this אונאה ona'ah category, right? Where
you have the two options and it says, and it says עד
שיראה. ad sheyireh. Okay, that's where you have a limited amount of
time. The question is, what's the story about these things? Do these
things kick in
automatically, right? Or are there or do you have also some time
some time with them? So let's see how the גמרא Gemara frames
it. Okay, איבעיא להו. ibaia lehu. We ask the following question. פחות
משתא לרבנן, pachos mishta lerabanan, less than a sixth where we say
it's מחילה. mechilah. לאלתר הוי מחילה le'altar havi mechilah or בכדי שיראה
לתגר או לקרובו? bikdei sheyireh letagar o likrovo? Is it מחילה mechilah
automatically? Because basically saying מחילה mechilah automatically is basically a way of
saying that that's a tolerable rate of overcharge, that's a, it's like
we can't be too precise, that's tolerable, it doesn't matter, automatically the
sale is final, there's nothing to be done about it. Or do
we say no, no, no, if you waited until you could show
and get advice and you didn't come back, then it's מחילה. mechilah.
But if you, but if you came back within a certain amount
of time, then you are entitled to get your money back. Okay,
because right, we say that this, right, okay, so that's the question.
When we say מחילה, mechilah, do we mean automatically, or do we
mean or do we mean only if you waited till you could've
till you could've gotten advice and you did nothing about it? So
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, ואם תמצא לומר בכדי שיראה לתגר
או לקרובו, ve'im timtza lomar bikdei sheyireh letagar o likrovo, if we
say it's not automatic, that actually if you come back right away
you can get your money back, okay, מאי איכא בין שתא לפחות
משתא? mai ika bein shteh lepachos mishteh? Then what's the difference? Here
if you come back within a period of time you can get
your money back, and here if you come back within a period
of time you can get your money back, right? So what difference
does it make once you hit a sixth? So the גמרא Gemara
says no, איכא, ika, here's the difference. דאילו שתא ידו על העליונה
רצה חוזר רצה קונה ומחזיר אונאה. de'ilu shteh yado al ha'elyonah ratzah
chozer ratzah koneh u'machzir ona'ah.
Because by here, when you do it within the period of time,
you have a choice. Your choice is do you want your money
back or do you want to reverse the sale? Whereas here, because
it's really pretty tolerable, you can't ask to reverse the sale, but
you can ask to get your money back.
Okay, דאילו פחות משתא קנה ומחזיר אונאה. de'ilu pachos mishteh kaneh u'machzir
ona'ah. It's definitely a good sale, the most you can do is
get your money back. So the question is, what is the idea
of when we say מחילה? mechilah? Do we mean automatic and then
what we're basically saying is just a tolerable rate of overcharge and
there's nothing to be done about it? Or do we mean it's
מחילה mechilah once you have actually forgone your rights, and you forgo
your rights after you had a chance to show and come back?
But if you come back within a period of time, you can
get your money back. Okay, so that is the question about how
about about that range. Okay, now מאי, mai, what's the story? Okay,
so so fine, so that's the question. So מאי, mai, what's the
story? So תא שמע, ta shema, come in here. חזרו לדברי חכמים.
chazru ledivrei chachamim. So now it's going to get complicated, okay, because
now it's talking about what was the חשבון cheshbon of these merchants
of לוד, Lod, whether they preferred רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon or whether
they preferred what the חכמים chachamim said. Okay, now וסברוה, vesavruha, we're
assuming
פחות משליש לרבי טרפון כפחות משתא לרבנן. pachos mishlish leRabbi Tarfon kipachos
mishteh lerabanan. That since רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, okay, and here is
going to be one third. Okay, this is רבנן rabanan and this
is רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. Now, רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon said you
go by a third, not a sixth. So we're going to assume
whatever we're going to say about the רבנן rabanan for this sixth,
we're going to say for רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon for the third
and down, right? Okay, so we're going to say all here this
is going to be a big מחילה, mechilah, okay, for the entire
amount, the same way we say here מחילה. mechilah. Now, we have
to assume, oh do you mean automatic or do we mean it's
מחילה mechilah only after you've waited the only after you've waited a
certain amount of time and haven't done anything about it? But the
first thing we're assuming is that the whole point of רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon saying a third is whatever they would say up to
a sixth, he's saying up to a third. That's pretty reasonable.
Now, אי אמרת בשלמא פחות משתא לרבנן בכדי שיראה לתגר או לקרובו.
ei amrat bishlama pachos mishteh lerabanan bikdei sheyireh letagar o likrovo. Less
than a
third, you can get your money back even less than a third
if it's within a certain amount of time
and for רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon, *Rabbi Tarfon* you can get your
money back the whole day if you come back any time in
the whole day. משום הכי חזרו *mishum hachi chazru*, then you understand
why they abandoned רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon*, meaning, if basically, if what
this is saying is, okay, if it really doesn't mean מחילה mechilah
*mechila*, what it really means is
you can get your overcharge back, okay, you can get your overcharge
back
within a few hours, okay? Right, that's what we mean בכדי שיראה
bichdei sheyera'eh, *bichdei sheyera*. If that's what we mean here, that you
have a few hours to get your overcharge back and then he
is saying you can get your overcharge back the whole day. So
if you were a seller, you would say, you would leave once
he said the whole day, right? When he said the whole day,
when he said a third they got happy. When he said a
whole day they want back. Okay? So they basically said, okay, great,
we can overcharge and get away with it. Even more we can
overcharge and get away with it, et cetera, et cetera. They got
the whole day to ask for their money back. Okay, oh, we'll
go here. They only have a few hours to ask for their
money back. We'd rather have less we can overcharge and make more
certain that they're not going to... we're going to get away with
it, okay? So you get it. If here you only have a
few hours and here you have the whole day to ask for
it back, you understand why they went back to being like the
חכמים *Chachamim*. Okay. אלא אי אמרת *ela ei amarta* משום הכי חזרו
*mishum hachi chazru*. אלא אי אמרת פחות משתות לרבנן לאלתר הויא מחילה
*ela ei amarta pachos mishtus lerabanan la'altar havya mechila*. But if what
this means is not you have a few hours to get it
back, it means automatically מחילה *mechila*. Okay. And then he's saying automatically
מחילה *mechila*.
So why would you ever go back?
Why would you prefer the...
now he said all day. But now what we're saying is when
you say those times, עד שיראה ad sheyireh. *ad sheyera* or all
day, maybe we only mean it for the אונאה ona'ah *ona'ah* stage,
not for the מחילה *mechila* stage. You understand the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*?
No, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says we know the period of עד
שיראה ad sheyireh *ad sheyera* applies to the אונאה ona'ah? *ona'ah* stage.
We want to know if it applies to the lower... to this
stage, the מחילה *mechila* stage. So if what we're saying is it
only applies to the אונאה ona'ah *ona'ah* stage, not the מחילה *mechila*,
and here you can never ask for your money back and then
here he's saying you can never ask for your money back, all
he's done is he's said when it's exactly a third, you have
more time. Okay, who the heck cares? Right? Which is what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. So when it's exactly a third, you got
more time to ask... who cares? When I have a huge amount
of time here where I'm going to get away with murder, right?
And they can't ask for their money back. So if this meant
that you can never get your money back and he's saying that
the same of under a sixth is like under a third, nobody
would ever want to go back to the חכמים *Chachamim*. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: ולרבי טרפון נמי לאלתר הויא
מחילה *u'leRabbi Tarfon nami la'altar havya mechila*. And for רבי טרפון *Rabbi
Tarfon* also it's automatically, so אמאי חזרו *amai chazru*? Why would they
go back? בדבי רבי טרפון ניחא להו טפי *bid'Rabbi Tarfon nicha lehu
tefei*. It's much better to be in רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon* land.
Okay. דמאי דרבנן קמטוו לאונאה *demai deRabanan kamatvu le'ona'ah* what the רבנן
*Rabanan* would consider אונאה ona'ah *ona'ah* or ביטול מקח bittul mekach *bitul
mekach*, okay, רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon* הויא מחילה *havya mechila*. It's going
to be מחילה *mechila*, they have no choice to ask for it
back. The only option to start asking for something back and giving
people some time starts at a third. So clearly on this space
below, you've got to actually say that also this is time-limited, that
the מחילה *mechila* idea is also a time-limited thing. So the גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara* says no. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*... ah, so that
seems to be a pretty good proof.
גמרא *Gemara* says no: מי סברת פחות משליש לרבי טרפון כפחות משתות
לרבנן דמי *mi savart pachos mishlish leRabbi Tarfon kepachos mishtus leRabanan dami*?
Who says that just because רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon* goes up to
a third, he treats this whole space like the rabbis treat the
under a sixth? Because it sounded like that. But okay, no. גמרא
*Gemara* says like this: No, מי סברת כפחות לרבנן דמי *mi savart
kepachos leRabanan dami*? לא *lo*, it's not true. משתות עד שליש לרבי
טרפון כשתות עצמה לרבנן דמי *mishtus ad shlish leRabbi Tarfon keshtus atzmah
leRabanan dami*. So what it's saying is like this: רבי טרפון
*Rabbi Tarfon* is
going...
he agrees that this is מחילה *mechila*, but what he does is
where the רבנן *Rabanan* have this אונאה ona'ah *ona'ah* sort of thing
and then ביטול מקח bittul mekach. *bitul mekach*, he makes all of
this אונאה ona'ah *ona'ah*. So the debate is not the מחילה *mechila*.
You can't prove anything about how much time... whether you have time
to ask for your money back down here. Maybe you don't have
any time to ask for your money back down here. But what
רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon* was... what they liked about רבי טרפון *Rabbi
Tarfon* was not that he extended the sense of מחילה *mechila*, but
he said it's not ביטול מקח bittul mekach. *bitul mekach*. This whole
space from a sixth to a third is this אונאה ona'ah. *ona'ah*
category and not a ביטול מקח bittul mekach *bitul mekach* category, okay?
And we are going to assume for argument's sake that the merchants
would rather it be considered אונאה ona'ah, *ona'ah* than it be considered
ביטול מקח bittul mekach, *bitul mekach*, okay? Why? I don't want to
get into right now, let's just focus on this. Assuming that they
would rather it be אונאה ona'ah *ona'ah* than ביטול מקח bittul mekach
*bitul mekach*, then what he is saying is he is treating all
of this as
אונאה ona'ah. *ona'ah* where the
Sages are treating most of
that as...
I know it doesn't.
Okay, so now let's see, let's try to get a little bit
further in this.
Okay. I know it's not in the משנה. Mishnah. Okay.
But okay, so the גמרא says, okay, אי הכי במאי סמכו מעיקרא?
ei hachi b'mai samchu meikara?
So why, so now the גמרא is going to ask that question,
okay, so why were they, if that's what the difference is, why
by exchanging ביטול מקח bittul mekach. for אונאה ona'ah. were they so
happy? I mean, now they're questioning what I just bracketed, right? So
he said, oh this is אונאה ona'ah, not ביטול מקח. bittul mekach
Like I don't understand, you know, אונאה in a way gives the
purchaser more options than ביטול מקח. bittul mekach So why were they
so happy that he called it אונאה? They could still ask for
your money back. You could still ask to be annulled the sale.
Why was this so much of a better choice than this? That's
a pretty good question, right? You understand? If all he's doing is
exchanging אונאה for ביטול מקח bittul mekach and אונאה gives the buyer
the choice of ביטול מקח, bittul mekach. why is that so much
preferable? Okay. So the גמרא says תפשוט tifshot according to this reading
we should conclude דביטול מקח לרבנן לעולם חוזר. de'bittul mekach l'rabbanan l'olam
chozer. Ah, here's why they preferred it. For ביטול מקח bittul mekach
could be forever.
אונאה is only עד שיראה. It has a clock on it. Okay.
So basically he said, right, עד שיראה is clearly going on the
אונאה category. It's not clear if the clock applies to מחילה and
the clock applies to ביטול מקח. bittul mekach What the clock clearly
applies to is the אונאה. That's clear in the משנה. So they
were very happy. Because forget the difference of אונאה, once he called
it אונאה that meant, oh, there's a clock on this. There's a
limited period of time. We'd rather be here where they only have
a limited period of time to ask for redress than ביטול מקח
bittul mekach where they can always get their money back.
It gives the security for the seller, רבי טרפון, once he calls
it אונאה.
Right, yeah. Right. כיון דאמר להו רבי טרפון הוי אונאה סמכו. keivan
d'amar lehu Rabbi Tarfon havei ona'ah samchu.
Then they were happy.
Now, כי אמר להו כל היום חוזר חזרו. ki amar lehu kol
hayom chozer chazru. Now of course the problem is that then even
if he says that it's כל היום, kol hayom, it's still כל
היום kol hayom is still less time than forever. Last I checked,
כל היום kol hayom was less time than forever. Okay. So רש"י,
Rashi, so this is where it gets complicated and you have a
big תוספות. Tosafot. רש"י Rashi basically says once you tell somebody כל
היום, kol hayom, if some like if you give only somebody only
a few hours, you're going to get away with a lot. If
you give somebody a whole day, then most likely if they, you
know, they have plenty of opportunity to be חוזר. chozer. So the
amount of opportunity that increases from a whole day to forever רש"י
Rashi says is very little. There's probably some truth to that, right?
You know, a certain amount of people like after a certain time
there's probably a huge drop off, like if you're not going to,
if you haven't done anything about it when you have a whole
day to do something about it, sure, there'll be a tiny percentage
that will use the fact that you've given me three months to
be חוזר, chozer, but anyway that's the argument, that there's a trivial
difference. What? So there's so right. But then the point is, okay,
even if I concede that there's a trivial difference, still why would
I go back and prefer this, right? So you know, that's not
clear, right? It's still this is still a little bit better than
this. So you have to say that no, somehow ביטול מקח bitul
mekach is better for them than אונאה. And that's part of what
I was saying before. Ironically, the ביטול מקח mekach is better for
them because it's less options for the buyer, right? If it's אונאה,
the buyer has can choose whether to get his money back or
ביטול מקח. So I'd rather have give the buyer less options because
then he's going to always choose what's in more his in his
own interest. Okay. ביטול מקח actually I'm allowed to also reverse it.
Not only can he reverse it, I can reverse it.
Would you prefer for the מקח to not be מתבטל mitpattel to
have that option?
Well, you don't know. No, but if the choice is being מתבטל
mitpattel or him getting his money back, I'd rather it be מתבטל
mitpattel and I can sell the same thing to somebody else and
get away with it, you know? So, so here's the irony. The
irony is that when you overcharge less, the more you overcharge, actually
you the seller are in a better situation. Now you have the
option of ביטול מקח and it's not that the buyer has all
the options. So once this is כל היום kol hayom and this
is forever, the difference in terms of the time is trivial. And
once the difference in terms of the time is trivial, as the
seller, I'd rather it be ביטול מקח and he not have all
the options and I have some options myself.
Yeah, it's very helpful. That's one of the things that you I
mean, although very helpful, the seller never wants to be in a
position where he's got to give the money back. Right. And not
get the product. Right, exactly. The seller doesn't want to give away
money.
Exactly, exactly. Because I'm just going to hold up because it's already
8:30 and I want and I know we have to start a
class here, I just need to read to the end of this
thought, okay? So the גמרא says like this, ואי סלקא דעתך כגמלו
כל יום דחזר ואי סלקא דעתך דביטול מקח לרבנן בכדי שיראה לתגר
או לקרובו ve-eesalka da'atakh k'gamlo kol yom d'chazar ve-eesalka da'atakh d'bitul mekach
lerabbanan bichdei sheyera'eh letagar o likrovo
because if this ביטול מקח is a limited amount of time, okay,
and then he's a כל יום, kol yom, there'd be or ever,
you know, whatever, there'd be no reason, if this is a limited
amount of time, you know, then anyway there'd be no reason to
go back, okay? במאי סמכו? b'mai samchu? Okay? So the גמרא, so
there'd be no reason to go back
if this were also limited, if this was בכדי שיראה, right, then
this is a much better place to be. It's כל היום. kol
hayom. This is very limited. So the גמרא says no, there could
still be a reason, we're getting out of here right now, there
could still be a reason why they would go back, although this
is going to be hard to believe. סמכו בשתות עצמה. samchu bish'tus
atma. No, no, no. Here clearly it's true. If this was כדי
שיראה, k'dei sheyera'eh,
they'd much rather be in this zone, okay, which is, which is
gives them a lot, which is... now I've totally lost my train
of thought.
You know what?
I think we'll have to pick up here. Oh man, I thought
I would get through that train of
thought.